Guide to the Mary Budd Rowe Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Mary Budd Rowe papers
circa 1990-1996
SC0552
Rowe, Mary Budd.
76 Linear feet
Papers include correspondence, reports, proposals, videos, publications, teaching materials, and other items largely pertaining to science education.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Information about Access
Access: collection is unprocessed; please consult the University Archivist for access.
Student files in boxes 1-2 are restricted for 75 years.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Rowe earned a bachelor's degree in biology and physics education from New Jersey State University in 1947, a master's in zoology from the University of California-Berkeley in 1954 and a doctorate in science education from Stanford in 1964. She taught at Columbia and the University of Florida and was a visiting professor at Stanford's School of Education from 1990 until her death in 1996. Rowe, an innovator in the use of technology to teach science concepts, headed the science education research division of the National Science Foundation from 1976 to 1980 and was part of the first science education delegation to the People's Republic of China in 1979.
Description of the Collection
Papers include correspondence, reports, proposals, videos, publications, teaching materials, and other items largely pertaining to science education.
Access Terms
Rowe, Mary Budd.; Stanford University. Graduate School of Education.; Education.; Science--Study and teaching.
Collection Contents
- Papers, Accession ARCH-1997-179
  - Stanford University School of Education (SUSE) administration, 1990-1997 (Box 1)
  - Student files A-B (note: contents may be confidential) (Box 1)
    Restricted for 75 years.
  - Student files B-Z (note: contents may be confidential) (Box 2)
  - Organization for Economic Co-Operation & Development (OECD) proposals, articles, correspondence (Box 3)
  - Memos, proposals, emails: technology, networkjng, Alice project. (Box 4)
  - MBR publications: articles, chapter reprints, reports (Box 5)
  - Funding proposals (Box 6)
  - Funding proposals. Correspondence and notes: sexuality & biology (Box 7)
  - Correspondence from educational foundations, other groups (Box 8)
  - Mail logs, annual reports, emails, MBR bio & CV (Box 9)
  - Budgets, research papers, speech material, meeting minutes (Box 10)
  - Conference materials (Box 11)
  - Education materials: publications, articles, handouts (Box 12)
  - Conference materials, appointment books, papers, reports (Box 13)
  - News, proposals, meeting minutes, correspondence with groups: Albion College – American Geological (Box 14)
  - News, proposals, meeting minutes, correspondence with groups: AGI – Chabot Observatory (Box 15)
  - News, proposals, meeting minutes, correspondence with groups: Chemunity News – Girls, Inc. (Box 16)
  - News, proposals, meeting minutes, correspondence with groups: Gordon & Breach – National Board for Professional Teaching Standards (NBTPS) (Box 17)
  - News, proposals, meeting minutes, correspondence with groups: National Coalition of Advocates for Science Scope, Sequence & Coordination Project, other misc. articles (Box 18)
  - HumBio project (Program in Human Biology) (Box 19)
  - HumBio, MBR articles, SUSE material, SU people files (note: contents may be confidential) (Box 20)
  - Newsletters, correspondence, Science & Health Education Partnership - Wufnicks (Box 21)
  - Calendars, conference materials (Box 22)
  - Vendor contacts, NBTPS meeting minutes, conference materials, memos (Box 23)
  - NBTPS material, OECD material (Box 24)
  - OECD, Chemcom material, reports on improving education (Box 25)
  - OECD, Chemcom material (Box 26)
  - SUSE faculty meeting notes, correspondence with individuals: Arctur - Saunders (note: contents may be confidential) (Box 27)
  - Correspondence with individuals: Small - Zellman (note: contents may be confidential), NBTPS project materials, Carnegie/PBS funding proposal (Box 28)
  - Memos, press releases, reports from organizations: PALM, Reading Rainbow, Galaxy., etc. Teaching materials: reserve readings, papers, evaluations (Box 29)
  - Teaching materials: reserve readings, papers, evaluations (Box 30)
  - Conferences, teaching materials. (Box 31)
  - Papers, article reprints on science, teaching techniques (Box 32)
  - Federal Coordinating Council for Science, Engineering & Technology (FCCSET) (Box 33)
  - Periodicals, articles, reports: testing/assessment, physics, computers, complex instruction (Box 34)
  - Periodicals, articles, reports: gender, memory, teaching, control, metaphor, & analogy, Science Helper/SHELLS (Box 35)
  - SHELLS material, scripts (Box 36)
  - Multimedia/CD-ROM teaching (Box 37)
  - Articles, reports (many by MBR). Correspondence. (Box 38)
  - Articles, reports, handbooks: networking, Internet (Box 39)
  - Various reports, SHELLS material (Box 40)
  - Reports and papers on teaching methods. SUSE material, including faculty meetings 1990-1991. (Box 41)
  - Books, periodicals, reports and papers on teaching methods (Box 42)
  - Mail logs, chron files 1990-91, emails, interview transcripts (Box 43)
  - Meetings, statements, projects of MBR 1995-96, teaching materials: notes, transparencies, etc. (Box 44)
  - Books, CD-ROMs (Box 45)
  - Videotapes, both published amp; unpublished. (Box 46)